This is software engineering radio the podcast for professional developers on the web at se-radio.net SE radio is brought to you by the ITE computer society and
by e software magazine online at computer.org/software.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio. I'm your host Gavin Henry and today my guest is Hector Ramon. And say your last name for me Hector.
Uh it's Jimenez.
Uh, Hector is a software developer from Spain who created ICE, Elm inspired crossplatform guey toolkit for Rust.
ICE has become one of the most popular Rust GUI libraries with around 30,000 stars on GitHub and a growing ecosystem of projects and crates.
He now works on ICE full-time, helping it mature and expand across desktop platforms.
Hector, welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
Is there anything I missed in your bio that you'd like to add?
No, no, that that was great.
Um, very glad to be here. Thanks for inviting me.
No, my pleasure.
So during the show, we're going to go over or try to cover five questions.
So we're going to try to understand why you created ICE.
We're going to understand what was needed.
Um we're going to explore the process required to paint on a screen across operating systems.
We're going to try to understand how multi operating system things are handled within ICE and
what the ICE testing ecosystem is like cuz I know there's a lot of cool stuff in 0.14 that I'd like to go over with you.
So let's kick off an introduction to lay the foundation.
I'd like to start with an overview of ICE.
So why did you create ICE?
It kind of happened as I got sidetracked from one project to another.
Kind of like ice happened as two sidetracks in a row.
Back in 2019, I wanted to make a a video game.
And I got sidetracked from that.
Ended up making a game library which I called coffee.
And this was in I chose Rust for it.
And you know back in the day the game dev ecosystem in Rust was very bare bones.
I was just getting started.
The graphics libraries were rudimentary.
There wasn't a lot of of things going on there.
So, I ended up kind of getting sidetracked and making my own game library because the ones that that were available weren't up to to my standard or not to my liking.
And at some point in my game, I needed a UI or a user interface.
And so, I added a little module to the game library that did UI.
And since before working in Rust, I was doing mainly web development and I got to use Elm for a while,
I've wondered if I could bring the Elm spirit into Rust and kind of like try to use or to create user interfaces using the the Elm architecture.
That's how I I created this UI little UI module in this game library for my game.
So it was like multiple things on top of each other.
And I remember that someone mentioned that it would be great to have this little module as a standalone thing of its own.
So like a library just to make, you know, just you may maybe you don't want to make a game, you just want to make a a UI or a UI application.
And I thought that that was an interesting idea.
And so I ended up kind of like splitting it apart and making it like its own thing.
That's how ice became to be.
originally wasn't even it didn't even have a proper like render or anything.
It was just a bunch of logic to position widgets and stuff and there wasn't a way to actually draw anything.
You had to write the entire drawing logic yourself when you pulled iced back in the day.
Oh, and where did the name come from?
Since the game library is called coffee, then then I just called it iced because I don't know, I just like iced coffee.
So, it was like there's there's nothing a lot deeper than that, honestly.
That's a cool origin of the name. Thanks.
So, what was needed and what was out there for you to create this first version, Hector?
There were like different things that I needed to build, but I was using mainly a library called win it, which is still a thing and it's and ice is still depending on it.
This is the windowing library that is the standard in Rust and absolutely everyone depends on it and I think it's actually understaffed.
it it needs more maintainers and it needs more contributors, I think.
So, yeah, if you're interested in contributing to that library, I think that they definitely could use help.
I'll put that in the show notes for everyone to have a look.
Yeah, cool.
Uh, and I ended up like needing some way to do layout, right?
So like way to position widgets and so on and ended up adopting a library back then called stretch which
implemented the flexbox CSS kind of strategy layout algorithm in Rust.
It was kind of hard to use and buggy at the time.
So we ended up removing that in ice.
We don't depend on it anymore.
And then yeah that was pretty much it.
Everything else was just built on top with I didn't actually have a renderer or anything.
So the library the first alpha version was just you know layout and windowing and that's mainly it.
What do we mean by a renderer?
So a renderer is something that takes the actual different widgets that the UI is made of like the UI representation of it like the layout and the state that the widgets are in.
Like for example, you have a button with some text and the button has some color, whatever.
The renderer basically grabs a window and draws that in it.
Like it it actually sets the correct color on the pixels of the the window so that you can see it in your in your screen. That's why it made my renderer.
So take us through the architecture and what attracted you to it.
Right.
The M architecture is like kind of like a natural way to build user interface applications and it kind of emerges naturally in the Elm programming language.
That's why it's called the Elm architecture.
And Elm is a purely functional language for front-end development for for the web basically.
And basically what it does, it forces you to split your application into different parts that are very well defined.
One is the state, one is the update logic and another thing is the B logic. And then you have messages.
And so the state of the application is basically the data or like what actually the actual data of the app like what's going on under the scenes, right?
To keep the actual continuous state of the application. Yeah.
And then you have the update logic which basically is a way to modify this state when the user interacts with the application.
And then you have view logic which basically takes the state and produces a description of the widgets that you want to display on your window.
So maybe you have a to-dos application and you have a bunch of like your state may be a list of strings, right?
So it's a it's a list of different tasks that you need to do plus a boolean for each task that says whether the task has been done or not.
And then the view logic takes this list and produces an actual description of where you want for example maybe you want to show a list of checkboxes.
So how do you want these checkboxes to actually be positioned on screen and so on.
And then the messages basically connect update logic and view logic together.
So the way that the architecture works is not by having callbacks on your widgets like you don't mix update logic together with view logic.
So you don't have on your button some kind of handler that when I click this I change this thing.
Instead what the ALM architecture does is when you press a button that produces a message of some sort like in Rust we have enums right which
are just uh some types right and that button produces this message and that message gets fed to the update logic and
so you have all the state mutation centralized in a single place that's what's interesting about Elm I think I was mainly attracted to it because
back in the day I was using angular I think and it was extremely painful to do any kind refactoring there were a lot of runtime errors.
I remember very vividly searching on Google JavaScript without runtime errors and that's the first match was and
and that's how I decided to give it a try cuz for me I was in so much pain just with this huge Angular codebase and after 2 weeks I had the entire app rewritten in Elm and it was such a bliss. So that's why I wanted to bring that back to Rust.
Well as you know I've been developing an app with ice for my son which allows him to communicate.
I'm quite familiar now with the Elm architecture and when you click that
button and you put a setting on it to say right this button message gets sent to the to the backend logic and
then that process it and the application state holds you know what screen that application might be on you know what the button was before what what you need to do when that button is pushed to look up.
So yeah, I think it was a good choice cuz it really makes my life and other ICE users lives easier when they want to add a new thing because we don't need to think about architecture.
We just wire something up of how we want it to look.
This is the message that gets sent.
We scoop up that message in the wherever we set it to be scooped up in the main RS file or whatever the design is there and we act on it.
And it's very nice and very easy to just come back a week later and go, "Oh yeah, that's how you do it."
There's no thinking about it. It's just there.
It's great. I think it plays very nicely with dynamic applications and generally the idea of having B logic take your state and
produce a projection of what the UI is is very flexible because you don't have to worry about like in other toolkits where you have to directly change the things that
are being displayed like I need to hide this button and I have to somehow change that directly right in in eyes you get a message and one message can potentially change the entire UI.
you can go from one screen to another and you don't really need to to tell the framework, you know, step by step how to do that.
You just you just describe the new UI and and ice takes care of it. Right.
Yeah. Exactly.
In your experience so far, have you seen anything out there that's similar to that's adopted this or that you go, "Oh, yeah, that's a good way to do that. I'll I'll steal a bit of that or contribute to that."
Well, I mean, the architecture had a lot of influence, I think, in many different projects before even.
I think that React for example has a similar philosophy.
It just doesn't have the message part but it's still you have some state and some view logic and
you're just you know recreating that tree that virtual the virtual DOM right they call it then you have projects like Redux which
they tried to bring they tried to bring the messages and the update logic part to react as well but
in Rust before eyes I think there was this project called realm which I think I think it's still a thing and I think it's uh basically a wrapper of GTK.
Maybe I'm wrong, but I think it's GTK that follows the M architecture.
So, it's wrapping GTK on and it creating like a Elm architecture API on top.
You can use GTK from Rust with a more or less nice API.
Cool.
I'll look that up and stick it in the notes.
What if you were really attracted to the Elm architecture, which is obviously HTML and things, what what made you switch to Rust or were you on Rust on Rust already and just brought that idea over?
So, back in the day, I was I always was involved in web development and I think that I just needed like a change of pace from the web.
I felt like it was kind of hard to target different browsers and the whole CSS thing.
I just didn't really enjoy it that much and I felt like maybe I can try to do something different for a while.
That's why I wanted to just that's why I decided to make a a game of my own.
I've always wanted to make like a little game and put it on Steam.
And I knew that I probably wouldn't get to finish it, but I was open to the idea of maybe I probably got sidetracked and see what happens from there.
And that's exactly what ended up happening.
And so yeah,
I chose Rust because it for me it seemed like the most mature or like the most modern option that didn't feel like going back to the stone age after trying functional languages like Helm and Haskell for native platforms, right?
So I considered using C, C++, but they don't even have a proper way to describe enumans, right?
Like a way to describe there's this type that can either be in value A or value B.
You you need to create like a strct with booleans or a union type of some sort.
It's not as straightforward.
And for me, once you develop once you go and you understand, I mean, once you code it with union types or with enums in Rust, there's really there's not really any way to go back.
I mean I wouldn't know how to go back and and code without them at this point I think.
Can you define a union for us in Rust?
Is that where you pass a value to an enum?
Yeah, an enum is the type that can either be like you you define the states that it can be and it's like a a disjoint choice, right?
So it's either you're in A, B, C or D, right?
And you can you can only have one instance of that, right?
So it's like a type that describes a set of potential values that it can have.
And this would be your marketing elevator pitch I suppose.
But why should someone use iced versus the other options out there like I
don't Tori or
Discuss is it or E GUI or the Z one or
so yeah why I'm trying to say I guess the main selling point is the ALM architecture it's I
think don't use the architecture they don't have the message passing part ei I is or eguey as I call it is immediate.
So it's very different in that you're uh mixing update logic together with deblogic and
I think it is more meant to be used on projects like games and something that where you need a quick integration of something rather than something that
scales up to complex applications probably can do it but I think the LM architecture helps you a lot more in that regard to keep things organized and yeah I think that's the main selling point.
Yeah, I guess people can just have a play and see what fits for them well.
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
In the end, it's it's all preference and,
you know, having having diversity and different choices is always good because it allows the communities to each community grows stronger when when you don't have to cram a bunch of people and we have different ideas together.
So, I'm going to move us on to the next part of the show and we're going to talk about the core of ice.
So, this is the the current version.
So what are the core components of ice if if that can be articulated?
Well, there are multiple pieces that ice wouldn't be like wouldn't be possible without one of them I already mentioned is win it the windowowing shell that
basically is the crate that takes care of creating windows in a crossplatform way and it exposes an API that's crossplatform and it's the same unified.
It tries to basically abstract away the tiny little details that come with all the windowowing managers and that's a huge effort because
windowing is craziness and and you have to abstract over Windows,
Mac OS and especially Linux where there's not even a there's not even a de facto standard of you know you have two different windowing servers right X11 and Wayland is not even a windowing server.
It's it's a protocol and then you have different compositors that are built on top and you know they have different extensions and it's pretty crazy and doing it is honestly amazing.
It has like a lot of issues in many ways but I don't think you can blame them because they're doing an amazing like it's just a very pretty complicated job.
Besides that, there's also WGPU, which is the main graph graphics library that we use.
Native implementation of the web GPU standard that is blended recently.
Well, it's I'm not sure if it's still everywhere in all the browsers. It's been getting there.
And it basically gives us an API as well that's crossplatform and allows us to draw to Windows in a way that's efficient and performant without having to worry about the platform differences or even backend differences.
So it abstracts over the different graphics APIs like Bulan Metal Direct X12 and it provides a single unified API that
that you can use to target all of them at once. So those two pieces are core twisted.
So Win in it creates sort of windows and the WGPU allows you to draw in those windows.
Yeah, correct. Yeah. And then the back ends metal will be Mac OS. Is it?
What are you asking exactly? You said Vulcan, Metal, and DirectX.
So DirectX will be Windows. Metal will be Apple. Is it?
Yeah. Metal will be Yeah. Yeah.
Vulcan is is that Linux?
Vulcan is available on Linux and Windows both.
Yeah. Okay, cool. All right.
No, sorry to interrupt. Just clarify. Cheers.
No worries. Um, so you've got the win in it for the drawing the creating the Windows WGPU to actually draw in the other back ends there and then what's above that?
There's a software rendering back end as well that we have that is currently built on top of Tiny Skia.
And Tiny Skia is a it's like a it's a small subset of the Skia rendering library that
was ported to Rust by Razer Falcon which
you know was was very involved in many different projects that come to to Rust UI.
Like I think he was an absolute monster back in the day.
I think that he's not as active anymore unfortunately.
But yeah, tiny scale basically allows us to draw or perform drawings efficiently just without leveraging the GPU at all. Right?
So WGPU uh leverages GPU acceleration which is very very fast right but
with tiny scale we can make ice work in you know devices that don't have a GPU right just have a CPU and
that's it maybe a virtual machine maybe embedded hardware so
that's also important part we are considering migrating from tiny ski to another project called bellow CPU now that is currently in the works and it's very promising so
you know this kind of stuff is always it's always changing The UI ecosystem is evolving and there's always like various solutions coming out, but tiny scale has been working well so far for us.
You'd think it would be something that was quite stabilized and solved ages ago, but things change a lot, don't they, I suppose.
Yeah. Yeah.
Honestly, it's crazy to see that 2D graphics I mean 2D graphics are very hard problem and
in Rust there's a lot of research being done and a lot of ground that's being broken in that direction.
I think so I think Bellow CPU is taking a complete new approach to 2D rendering.
I'm not a graphics wizard so I can really give them any more details about it but I've heard that there's like a thesis of some student that's that's working on it. So yeah it's very very promising.
And do you think these this progress is because people are wanting to get away from C++ type renderers or graphics things they rely on and have it in pure Rust or what do you think?
They're just discovering new ways to do things.
I think Rust is a language that once you try it, you love it, right?
And people get very passionate about it.
And it just what I said, it feels very hard to go back to these other languages.
In a way, the way I think about it is that if you're building a new project and you're choosing C++ today, you're you're doing a bit of of a disservice in in the sense that you could choose Rust and I think you're going to have like a better time.
It's going to be memory safe and you're going to have a more precise way to describe the different problems you're going to have to encode or like deal with.
I've done quite a lot of shows on Rust and so is the other hosts.
So we've got show 672 with Luca Palriia on Rust in production.
Matus Enler on prototyping on Rust which is really cool interesting.
Brandon Matthews on ideatic rust and then we had one with Tim Mara on error handling and a few others.
So they're they're in the show notes for yourself and others as well.
So I'm going to move us on to the next question.
So I think I summarized what you'd explained that you use win in it and when GPU and tiny skier if there isn't a GPU on the system.
Can you just remind us I think we touched a bit on it in the introduction.
So you have widgets.
Could you take me through the process to put a line or button on the screen across different operating systems given the fact we've kind of touched on the libraries that help to do that.
You want to know how a button goes from I guess being described by like ice is hey here's a button and
how that that that gets you know displayed on the window right yeah I think that just help visualize the whole thing right so
the way it works ice has this still called a runtime right so the runtime is just when
you start your app there's a loop basically an infinite loop that runs constantly until you know you exit the application or quit it right so what is ice does first It opens a window, right?
So for that it uses winit and that you know opens a window and what you obtain when you open a window is a surface right and
a surface is like the actual the actual region on screen that you are allowed to draw into.
Then with that you pass that to the renderer in this case WGPU and then you get an actual texture where you can perform rendering operations.
And so what is ice does is it creates this window.
It creates a renderer for it with a surface and then it starts the LM architecture loop which
basically calls this boot function of your application which creates the initial state right and then we have this task based system.
You can fire asynchronous actions concurrently right.
So you can have things running in the background if you want but for simplicity let's let's just leave that for later if anything.
But the idea is it creates the initial state of the app and then from here it calls the BU logic right.
The BU logic is a function just a function that takes the state of the app the current state and then produces a element right and
an element is just a description of the UI that you want to display.
So an element can be any widget right?
It's like a generic widget.
So you could have like a column of three buttons or something like that.
that will be an element that column containing the buttons.
So widgets can contain other widgets basically and then it will take this element and then it will run a layout logic.
So ice needs to figure out now how these elements want to be positioned right and that is going to depend on the contents of the elements.
So if it's a column you want to position these elements vertically right one on top of the other.
And for doing that you need to know well the sizes of each of the elements first.
So it's a bit of like you're just delegating forward.
So you cut a column call the layout on the button and I have to lay out the button and then the button may have some text.
So now you need to figure out the size of the text and so on.
And eventually you know you perform some calculations and you get the layout figured out and from there with the layout you can draw it right and for drawing it you just pass it through the renderer logic.
And the render logic basically just a bunch of operations that take the layout of the widget and the current state of the widget.
So for example, if the widget is currently being hovered or or or the but the the button is being hovered or pressed, you probably want a different color on the background, right?
To signal that interaction to the user.
So that's what the render logic does.
It dials a button and uses different colors based on that.
And then these operations are recorded internally as WGPU commands that eventually are processed into geometry which
normally are like a a list of triangles,
right, that you send to the GPU and the GPU executes some shader code and shaders are like little programs that
the GPU can run and that's what they actually performs the painting in the in the texture and then the texture once you have it you can like say now I want to present it and that's when
the the actual GPU sends the data to the monitor, let's say, and you see the actual button.
There's a lot of different moving parts.
I love it. I think that's the best explanation I've ever had of how to paint on the screen.
Just to be clear, most of that, if not all of it, I don't do. It's something that ice does.
I don't have to think about rendering it or speaking to these libraries.
I literally just saying right my view contains elements which like you said could be a row or a column and they might be macros or
I built the strct myself and I compose what I want it to look like and as long as the by the end of that my function returns the element or
you know the last bit as an element then it meets what the view needs and then it goes from there.
Yeah, exactly.
you only need to worry about two different parts in in ice which is how do I go from state to this element description right like the view logic and
then when there's an actual interaction that happens how do I change the state and then you know the the ice takes care of the rest it just does this loop where
every interaction triggers the update logic and when the state changes anything that
triggers the state change then you need to call view again to get the new representation right in fact Rust is Great in this sense because
the borrow checker forces you statically at compilation time to call view logic.
ICE cannot call your update logic without dropping the widget tree first basically.
So we are like the library is forced by the compiler to call view logic again after there's an actual mutation on your state.
We cannot we cannot mutate the state without letting go of your previous widget representation basically.
So I think we've covered elements, we've covered how to paint on the screen, we briefly mentioned tasks and asynchronous functions.
So we better dig into that a little bit and some states.
So we've got these messages that fly between the view and the sort of main application logic.
Now when that message comes in, for example, you push a button, we want to send back an enum that says message colon colon whatever we decided to call it.
Now the as far as I understand it there's a match that goes through every enum we've defined in that message strap in that message enam because it's Rust it has to do something and
on the arm of the match and then that triggers the the review.
Stop me if I'm speaking rubbish here.
So what I'm trying to get to is we need to decide to do something when that message comes through.
So that might be to immediately change the look of the button or that button might fire off a download or playing some audio or something that
takes more than the screen needs to refresh, you know, so it's going to take 2 seconds, 1 second, whatever. That would be a task, wouldn't it?
Yeah, correct. Yeah.
So naively, you could say, well, if I want to download something after you press a button, for example, maybe I can just do that in update like in the update logic.
The problem is that the update logic runs in the main thread.
So because you have access to the state and you can mutate the state of the app, if you if you do the download there, you're going to block the entire UI, right?
So what what the user will see is the the spinning wheel basically, right?
And while the download is going and that's not normally what you want in a UI.
You want to do that in the background, maybe have a progress V of some sort, get notified of the progress of the download.
Yeah, I got that when I first started on Linux.
It says this application is frozen.
Do you want to force quit it or wait?
You know, I guess that was the blocking bit.
Yeah. Yeah. Exactly.
Because again, the borrow checker won't let us call Vue until updates done.
We cannot mutate the state of the app while the while there's view logic being used in any way. Right?
That's because Vue logic is allowed to borrow from application state.
So it can actually you can actually capture references from application state directly like maybe you have a long list in your in your app or or a bunch of data there.
You can the widgets can actually borrow it efficiently and use it to to display things directly without needing to clone all that data.
However, that means that because of, you know, the borrowing rules, you can't really change that while it's being displayed because that can cause,
you know, all kinds of memory issues that rust will just not allow.
So that's why we we have the task system and the task system is just update logic can return which
is you know just a function can return a task that it basically is just a future in Rust and you know you can there perform anything you want concurrently.
So you return this task which doesn't actually execute anything but it's just like a closure or a description of what you want to do and then the runtime will run that
in a different thread and when it's done it will send or produce a message back to the update. Right.
Exactly. Yeah.
That's that's how I'm doing certain things as well.
We've spoke about state a few times.
Should we just practically describe what that would look like in Rust?
like in our main RS file.
It might be a structure or it might be another file we've included.
It's just somewhere where we mutate things, you know, could be a big structure or many. How would you describe it?
Yeah, normally is a strct.
It could be an enum too depending like for instance a very common pattern is if you if your application has to load things at startup maybe you have an enum that
has a loading variant and then another one that's the actual oh it's loaded and now you know I have all this data over here but
in the end it's just it's just an actual type with some fields in it and some data that's what we consider state it's nothing more complicated than that cool thanks so
you touched on my next question luckily so there's the application state where you might use enums.
So that could be like a pattern I suppose.
Are there recommended patterns that you would advise people to start with in a nice application or read about some or what would you advise?
I have a problem with the word pattern.
Maybe it's just PTSD from the whole design patterns back in the day when I was into object-oriented programming and you know I learned about all these dependency injection and observer and all that stuff and I just wanted to use it everywhere.
ended up creating a lot of chaos.
But yeah, I think that there are some things that kind of emerge naturally as you're using iced and that a lot of people end up kind of relying on and using like for example, you know, this loading enum, right?
Or another thing that people tend to call the component pattern of some sort where you may want to split your messages and
create like a sub message enum that nests messages together and then you have like a little reusable part of your UI which
is just a message update view like a little part of the the architecture they're just splitting and creating like a sub application and then you're just connecting that to the parent app or something.
The thing is that you know the Elm architecture kind of composes very well.
You can split it and nest it if you want and so you can create boundaries between things that are quite nice.
However, when you do that, there's always a downside, let's say, where you're splitting state at the same time, right?
So that means that you're not going to be able to access state as easily from everywhere else in your application.
So you need to be very sure that the state that you split and create a component of, right, you're kind of like encapsulating them some way.
You got to make sure that that's not something you're going to need to access from,
you know, other parts of the app and maybe mutate it or whatever cuz then you run into synchronization issues,
especially if you are going to have multiple of these components at once and you need to, I don't know, somehow keep them synchronized or something.
Thanks.
So, I think we've done a good overview of the core of ICE.
ICE has got many, many things, but we've chosen the core bit to chat about.
What are some of the least well-known parts of ICE you've worked hard on or someone's contributed that you don't think many people know about?
And where I'm going with this is every now I'm on the ice discord, the sort of chat rooms, and every now and again one of your 3D demo comes up that looks amazing, but I've never seen anyone else use it or do or do similar.
So there must be some really good bits that are not so common.
The shader widget is the 3D widget that you mentioned.
Yeah, it's uh it's quite cool and it's underused.
I think that well I've seen some libraries actually rely on it. So that's nice.
I think that it was for charting that they were using it.
But yeah, another thing that I see underappreciated a lot is the the documentation is something that a lot of people have issues with.
They just notice that there's not enough of it.
But the current amount that there is, there's been a lot of work put into that. Sure, there's it's not enough.
I'm aware of that.
But I think that until you actually go and like have an actual open source project and try to write documentation for it, you do not realize how much work it goes into it.
Just just creating the actual diagrams to explain the different parts of the library and then trying to you know explain it in nice terms.
It's very tricky in the sense that not only you need to actually write the documentation, but the the library needs to be in the proper shape to actually be able to explain it in simple terms, right?
So, it's a bit of a test as well when you write documentation.
It's like if you can do it, it means that probably the library is easy to use, right?
If it's not, then you're going to have a bad time writing it.
So, that's definitely one one thing that I would like to see more appreciation for.
Yeah, I've read it all. I really enjoyed it.
I'm hoping to contribute because that's been part of the my open source life is helping with documentation.
So once I learn a bit more, I should be along to help.
Yeah, that that'd be great.
I don't really take contributions on the book directly, but I think that anyone can like any kind of blog post or you know unofficial writing or like that's that's great.
I mean there's there's a couple unofficial guides that are really amazing and they're community maintained.
Yeah, I'll get those in the show notes for everyone.
Uh, so there's anything else in the least well-known parts?
There's some widgets that are very niche like there's a sensor widget that you can use to u be notified when certain things are displayed or
hidden from view which I think I think it's under underused.
I think you can do very cool stuff with that like infinite scrolling lists and stuff like that.
Yeah, I'm actually using it in my application one talker.
a user wants to put a symbol on a button because that button means something to them.
Uh, bring up an image picker that has like 4,000 SVGs in it because it might describe an airplane, a packet of crisps, you know, whatever it is they're trying to do.
So, when they click the all category that has every button, as you're scrolling down or using your finger, it triggers the sensor and then I go and fetch the ne next block.
So, it's kind of like an infinite scroll, but it's got a limit because there's only like 4,000 symbols in the library, but it keeps it really snappy. It was really nice. Really like it.
That's awesome. Yeah. It's like one of the main use cases for it. I think it's precisely that.
Yeah, cuz it's kind of got this bit where it says I'm almost on the screen, so you better start doing things.
I'm on the screen.
You know, it's got like a sort of hidden buffer shadow or whatever you want to call it. I don't know. But yeah, that was good. I've not seen that in other places.
Yeah.
I mean, I think eventually we would probably want to have some kind of infinite list widget of some sort or or support this use case more more in a more direct way so
that you don't have to do this juggling with sensor, but I'm not sure if that's going to be something that we'll use sensor internally anyways and we just be, you know, it will be maybe just a crate or a library on its own.
Okay, I'm going to move us on to the next section.
Um, so I think I got on board with ICE before 0.14 was out because we were chatting about doing the show and
you wanted to get that out the door first, but I didn't really appreciate the sheer size of that release.
It was a it was a big one as far as I understand anyway.
And I was really impressed with the testing additions and I'd like to chat about those if it's okay.
The testing stuff is very very work in progress and experimental, but yeah, we can talk about it. It's it's it's fun.
Cool.
Is there anything else in the 0.14 release that you want to highlight before we get into the testing bit because we've got a bit of time?
I think the main highlight was the what was it called like reactive rendering right where like in the very beginning iced well not in the very beginning before 014 ice basically rendered all the time.
So if you were moving your mouse on your window, every single little mouse event, right, would cause a complete redraw of the entire application. That's been fixed in 014.
So the widgets now know when they're being interacted with and they're triggering re the redraws themselves instead of like just pessimistically assuming that everything needs to be redrawn all the time.
So that that's an important improvement in 04.
I think I actually noticed that because when you've got debug logs, debug statements everywhere because you're just learning or you're trying to figure out how how your application's progressing.
I moved my mouse and I was like, "Oh my god, I can't even read all of that.
It's just screaming fast."
And I think on 14 it went cuz I wasn't interacting with things. That's good.
So you you started using 013, I guess.
Yeah, I started with that and then I just switched to the main GitHub branch.
So, master and then when it stabilized, I thought I'll just see if everything works with 14 and I wasn't touching anything that wasn't stabilized. So, I'm still on that at the moment.
Another thing that kind of is interesting and like it was something that I always wanted to implement or try implementing it and ended up landing in 014.
It's very experimental but it kind of works is that the Elm architecture since it has this message based uh architecture right like where
you have you know view produces messages and these messages are fed into update and all the all the state mutation happens in a centralized place.
What this allows is technically to recreate any state that the application has been in since the very beginning. Right?
Because if you have the messages and all the state mutations happen through messages,
you can store these messages and if you have that copy then you all you need to do is I recreate the initial state and
I just process the messages until you know any given point and so I can recreate the state of the app at any point in time.
And so with this I uh implemented a companion app called Comet which is also made in that you can bring up with F12.
And if you enable the time travel feature flag, you can basically time travel back in time to any point in the execution of the application, right?
So you can see your application at any point in time since it spawned basically.
And that's very useful for stuff like animating things for example, like if you want to see the transition of an animation,
you can you can use this feature to to like see exactly each each of the frames that were drawn and so and so forth.
Yeah, I played with that.
I like comet where you can see how long different things take to render and you can debug stuff. It's really good.
So, I just want to clarify. I think we've already done this, but update view, they're just functions, aren't they? They're just Rust functions.
Yeah, normally they're just methods on the the state or whatever type you have.
But, you know, methods are just functions in Rust with the self uh argument.
Yeah, I think I've just passed in an application state thing, but yeah.
Cool. Okay, so testing.
I've played with both of these, so I want to dig into them a bit.
So, what is headless headless mode testing and how do you support it?
Right.
Headless mode testing is Well, the other question first is what is first class endto-end testing?
Should we do that one first before headless mode or what do you think?
You need headless mode for for that one.
So, I guess we could do headless first.
Yeah.
So headless is basically a way to to like run your application without an actual window, right?
So kind of without win it whatsoever and without potentially without even a renderer at all and
just have um like a like a kind of like there's there's like you can just drive your app or your app logic without displaying it whatsoever.
So it's just it's as if it's being displayed.
The app doesn't know that it's not.
But that way you can just, you know, actually test it in an environment where there's no maybe no windowing manager or not even a renderer.
So, so that's what headless mode is.
It's just a way to run your application as if it was being displayed as if it was an actual user interface, but there isn't actually any.
You're just testing it like you're just running it in an environment that there's there's actually no window. It's just being emulated, right?
Yeah.
because you've broken up that process with the different other Rust projects or within heist, you can just kind of stop it there and not move on to displaying things.
Yeah. Yeah. Kind of kind of like that.
The part of the Elm architecture, right, that's the the part that you define of the application.
So the update logic, message, and B logic is all that's really needed.
And then what you actually plug into that if it's the actual real thing that displays a window and draws things or you choose to instead plug it to something else that just pretends to be doing those things.
That's up to the actual runtime to do that. Yeah, you can decide that later.
Okay.
So what is first class end to end testing?
I've got a big list in brackets that I'll just throw out here.
I've got test recorder, runtime emulator, program presets, ice test syntax, and a selector AP.
So, if we can go over all of those, we might not have time, but so rephrase the question, what is first class endto-end testing?
Yeah, first class end to end testing is kind of like a vision I have where
I would like for to provide not only a way to build UI apps, but also a way to test them from uh end to end.
So the idea is that you can use this little uh language or
this little DSL domain specific language right that
you can use to describe user interactions like I click this button and then after I click this button I want to I want to check that
there's actually this text being displayed right so that's basically what first class to end testing is just a set of tools that
ICE provides by default that allow you to If you're for example, I don't know, you're building a to-dos application.
Well, it allows you to describe what kind of like requirements the application needs to satisfy from a user perspective.
So, you can define user interactions and what's the state that you expect or what what does the user expects to see after those interactions have been carried out.
Yeah, I've played with the test recorder, I think.
So, I was just and this will be a common scenario, I think, for someone moving through creating an application.
you might redesign something or you add another feature to a button push or something like that and you just want to make sure that you've got this safety net as you're moving forward that when you change one thing it's not going to break something else.
So the test recorder I enjoy. Do you want to take us through what that is?
Yeah, a test recorder is a bit of, you know, an experiment.
And the idea is that well, what you actually want for for a test is to describe user interactions, right?
I wanted to create this little tool that instead of like writing them manually, why not just click record,
have like a some way to click record in the app and then as you are interacting with it, the interactions are being like saved and recorded, right?
And then at the end you can you can choose to create expectations like hover so some text and then you know it will say expect this little thing to be there.
Sorry is that interaction the application state you're logging as in what message was pushed or you actually recording the mouse going over you know being dragged across the screen.
It's a bit like I'm recording the actual events that it's it's the actual mouse but not exactly because there's like a translation process that goes on to make things a bit more consistent or like not as brittle, right?
Because if I just store the mouse movements or the clicks and the coordinates themselves, that is very brittle if your application kind of changes or moves things around a bit, right?
Because you know a button may change position slightly and now you're not clicking that anymore.
So instead, what the recorder tries to do is tries to tries to figure out exactly what you what you're what you're clicking or what widget you're clicking and then it tries to find uniquely identifying things.
So for example, maybe the text that's inside the button is unique in the current screen.
So we can use that and then say instead of clicking in this coordinates, we say click this the widget that contains this text.
So that's what's actually saved in the test itself, not the actual coordinate.
So there's like a translation part.
There's also a merging of instructions as well.
So when you move the mouse over the window, it's not actually saving all these movements, right?
Because most of the time when you are moving the mouse in an app, that's that doesn't cause any actual interaction or anything.
It doesn't really care about it.
So instead what it does it just merges all the movements together all the coordinates and
instead of producing like a thousand different mouse movements right it just actually summarizes it in the last the last coordinate is the one that
matters right excellent and I've got a note here of a runtime emulator what's that
right the runtime emulator is basically once you've recorded a test right you want to be able to run it in headless mode without actually any window or anything.
Just just want to make sure that it runs and that's it.
Make sure that it passes.
You don't want that to produce a window or any renderer whatsoever. Just want to run that.
And so the emulator is just like a sandbox that runs tests, this tests that you recorded as if it was an actual app being run and displaying things.
And so it tries to create this virtual environment for them to run.
Yeah, sounds very powerful to be able to have like a QA engineer or something like that just go through and really batter your application and make sure you can um do things.
Yeah, that's the that's the entire purpose of this.
I'm building this feature for for work because we recently hired a QA engineer there and
we're building a we we we develop a nice app and
so the goal is for them to be able to use this feature to test this application like heavily and we're not quite there yet.
Yeah, I think I need to report a bug cuz I had a crash when I was just clicking some of my buttons just froze.
Didn't record it so I couldn't click playback.
But I'll open an issue for that later.
Okay, I'm going to move us on to last section now, I think.
Unless there's anything there you wanted to cover off.
We mentioned program presets and ice test syntax.
Yeah, the program presets are just uh they're like different ways to create the initial state of the app.
So often in in tests right when
you want to test something you don't want to start from the initial state of like from scratch right
you just want to have like set of maybe you can have a preset that's like I want a new user in this particular screen and then the test can start from there right so
that's what a preset allows you to do it just allows you to define given initial state right that the programmer can define for the QA engineer to just set whenever you're recording and was the nice test syntax. The DSL you were talking about.
Yeah, that's the DSL.
That's the actual that's the actual thing that gets stored when you finish the recording.
It's just a list of instructions that it's in the end a very simple programming language.
It's just a list of click here, expect this thing here, um move mouse over there, you know, that kind of stuff.
Yeah.
I think there's similar things in the HTML world, isn't there?
When you can just record a browser session and then play it back.
Yeah. Yeah, like selenium.
Even in other toolkits, you have things like cucumber, I think, or gerkin, right? The girkin thing.
Yeah, cucumber, I think, is the elixir, is it?
Yeah, I've used that in the security burp suite as well when you're trying to sort of test the security of a web application.
You can record all your clicks and then it'll play it back and try and attack everything.
Anyway, sorry.
Okay, so I've called this last section, what's next?
So, what are your plans for 0.15 or are we going to go to version one and why not?
Yeah, I think version one is very far away still.
It's so heavily weighted though.
Everyone, this is like two camps.
It's either like 0.98151, you know, it never gets to one or version one is that first time you make a commit which is kind of that is version one really, isn't it?
Yeah, true.
I mean technically if your project is being used in production and being dependent on it should be version one right I think that's is that
how semantic versioning defines it yeah it's just there seems to be the rust world where
everything looks like 0 something you know everyone's scared to just put a big one something on it or
2 point something yeah for me it's a bit about messaging and and communicating the state that the library is in right and that is something I take very seriously.
I mean, I use this experimental software and it's really just my pet project.
So, it's not really it doesn't really come with any stability guarantees at this point. I don't even know how I'm going to be tackling different things.
Everything is very experimental even after all this time.
So, the uh zero point notation kind of gives this at least tries to make it clear, hey, this is not something that you should be using seriously really. But you know, people use it anyways.
Yeah, we are. We're all using it seriously for very important things.
So that doesn't work.
Yeah, true.
But I still don't want to, you know, commit to like I cannot really commit to a stable release.
I mean, in the end it would be just the semantics thing like yeah, I'm putting one on the front, but I'm going to have two next, right?
It's not like I'm going to be supporting 10.
And the idea is that whenever we get to 10, I want to be able to say, well, this is more or less the fulfilled vision of what a what a complete release of ICE would would look like.
I understand. Do you plan? Yeah.
So, what what do you think's going to be in 015?
So far, we've we've added uh I think we've added text ellipses, which was also, you know, it's it's kind of nice to have it.
I think that, you know, text can now have like this little three little dots at the end if it doesn't fit and stuff like that.
Um, but the big features that are going to land um are I think accessibility is the main thing that I want to look into.
So supporting screen readers and integrating more with uh with you know like uh um the the accessibility APIs of the different platforms.
There's a rust crate I think it's called access getit that should abstract away the details.
So it just has a crossplatform API.
I think it's been done before.
I think that the the folks at system 76 have implemented accessibility on top of their ice for.
So that's something I'm definitely going to be using as inspiration.
What who are those guys again? Who's system 76?
System 76.
They've adopted ice for the pop OS new cosmic desktop environment.
So they're they're using ice.
They're using a fork of ice for for developing a new desktop environment for Linux basically.
So that's a pretty big stamp of approval, is it not?
Oh yeah. Yeah, it definitely is.
It I think it's it's brought a lot of, you know, attention to ice contribute a lot of things as well, don't they?
Yeah. Yeah.
I mean the main thing that they've contributed is the cosmic text right which
is the the library that we use to rely on you know to like uh lay out text and draw text and so on that back in the day when
I started was not a thing at all it there was nothing you would have to use C++ dependencies or
depend on the system APIs for that and there's been a lot of work done in that action in the Rust ecosystem and now we are at a place where
you know we can sort of display different kinds of text more or less in an acceptable way now.
So that's awesome.
That's definitely a huge contribution that they did.
Do you plan to keep ice desktop only?
Cuz I see a lot of pull requests for Android and iOS.
So why is that hard you know in your to do?
I plan on keeping ice desktop only mainly because I I cannot really commit to maintaining mobile at all in the sense that
I don't really have any use cases or I don't really develop uh mobile applications myself.
So I it would be hard for me to test the things like to test the changes properly.
Also the idea that I don't think it's possible to target mobile and desktop applications properly with a single unified API.
I think that mobile is a very different platform with very different needs where
battery life is important being very performant is important and I'm not sure the Elm architecture you know plays very well with that
because you know in the end it's just it's it's good for very dynamic applications but
we do redraw very often maybe eventually we will have something like some ways to know what precisely has changed in the window so
that we only redraw partially certain parts which is called incremental rendering.
But but yeah, there's like a lot of different use cases that mobile has requirements, let's say that I'm not sure I have the like the bandwidth to tackle everything.
It's already very hard and challenging to just tackle desktop and all the differences that you have with Mac OS and and uh Windows and Linux.
Just adding iOS and Android to the equation would be pretty insane, I think. Thanks.
I'm going to start wrapping up now.
I think hit our limits for the show.
Before I do, what apps would you recommend people go play with to get a feel for Ice Store?
You know that you're you look at and go, "Wow, that's really cool.
I helped build that, you know, as it were."
If you go to ice.rs, there's a showcase there and you know, some of the best applications I think that well, you have popos with a new cosmic desktop environment.
That's that's a fork of ice, but in the end it's the same architecture.
It's the same idea.
And then there's also Holloway.
I had to I had to shout out Holloway because, you know, the people involved are friends of mine and it's just an amazing IRC client. Very simple.
And IRC is making a comeback, I think, now that Discord is going all full on surveillance mode. So, so yeah, you can go and try it out.
I think it's it's nice.
I've got this showcase in the show notes and halli already actually.
Cool. Were you happy that we covered everything that you wanted to mention for 0.15?
I think accessibility there's also well with accessibility comes uh centralized focus management or keyboard navigation of some sort.
So that's something missing right now in what about internationalization multi- language?
Can you do that already?
You can do it on on top of yeah on top of ice basically like you pull a crate like fluent or something and then you just do it in your blog.
You plug the you know whenever you have a string you just call a function that takes care of it. There's no built-in way to do it.
I'm not sure it's necessary to support it first class in the library.
I have to be convinced that that's something we need to support or I will have to be shown.
Yeah, this is something that cannot be done well from like just by pulling a crate.
Well, that's good. You just helped me cuz I didn't know about that crate.
I'm going to write that down and use it myself.
Yeah, it's not a crate. It's like a platform, I think.
But there are some crates to So, yeah, let's start wrapping up.
I've really enjoyed chatting to you and exploring ICE with its creator.
Was there anything we missed that you'd have liked to mention or did we cover everything?
I think I think that was that was pretty thorough and yeah, I'm happy with it.
So, if people want to find out more, how can they get in touch or reach out?
Can uh send me an email to Hectorh.dev
or they can just come to my GitHub. It's h ecg or, you know, just come to the ice discord.
We're we're we're probably migrating to Zulip soon.
If you go to the to the repo in the readme, you can you can find ways to just add some links to the show notes.
So, Hector, thank you for coming on the show. It's been a real pleasure.
This is Gavin Henry for Software Engineering Radio. Thank you for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an educational program brought to you by E Software Magazine.
For more about the podcast, including other episodes, visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on each episode on the website or reach us on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or through our Slack channel at seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at teamse-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio is licensed under Creative Common License 2.5. Thanks for listening.